[Music]
Hi and welcome to this session on
smarter pipelines. My name is Espos
Kustavson and I'm an architect on the
Business Central developer tools team.
Managing pipelines for a larger repo
with many AL projects can be a pain
which is something we have now addressed
with this couple of features that are
the topic of this presentation.
We have added a way to centralize
application settings across projects
that is easily managed in a pipeline. We
have also created a simpler and faster
way to get access to your command line
tools in a pipeline. Together those two
features should help you streamline your
pipeline pipelines.
So what is the problem? This here is a
snapshot of our BC apps repo. You are
probably aware of that. It's available
on GitHub. In this repo, there is more
than 200 app.json files. And whenever we
create a new major, a new minor at doing
a build, we need to update the version.
We could of course create a PowerShell
script that changes all those app.json
JSON files and create a commit with
those changes.
But doing that every time we do a build
in the pipeline for this repo would be a
mess. So we don't want to do that. And a
commit with 200 plus changes is also a
bit excessive if what we want to change
is just the major and minor versions for
those files.
So what have we done to address this?
We came up with a new file inspired by
the MS build props file. We have now
created a file called
directory.app.props.json.
And that file has two sections. It has a
variable section. And inside the
variable section, you declare variables
that you can assign a value. And those
values can be overridden by
environmental values from variables.
the properties sections the the
properties in there map to the
properties in app.json if you have a
property in there it can be used if that
property is absent in app.json
as you can see here in this example
in the variable section I have
constructed the version as a variable
based on the major minor build and
revision variables. So I can use that I
can use the placeholders in there to
create a new variable. And if you then
look in the property section, you can
see I have the version down there. In
this case, it is a replacement for a
version property in the app.json
and I used the version I created in the
variable section as the value for that
one. This means that if I want to create
a new revision, I can just change the
revision variable
and then it will end up in the version
property.
Let's see how that works.
I have a workspace here with three
projects in. They are simple because
doesn't matter what they're doing. A, B,
and C. And I have in the folder above
and you can see that down here in the um
terminal window which is just a listing
of the directory above the three
projects there is a directory
app.props.json file which is the one I'm
looking at here and it's similar to one
on the slide. There's a version section.
I have the version down here and I have
another a couple of other properties
declared here. So now let me look at
this app.json file here for the first
project a you can see here this is
standard app.json generated by go and it
has all the properties
but let me I mean let me take this the
version get rid of that
and normally doing this now you would
get an error saying you need a version
in an app.json JSON file, but in this
case it actually finds the one in the
props file. So I can get rid of that. I
can do the same for the publisher
because I also had a publisher property
in the directory file.
And these and the privacy statements and
the platform
all of those are actually present in the
props file which means that I don't need
them here.
And what it also means is that if I do
this for all my projects, I can use that
to have a single place where I can
change the specific properties for all
my projects.
Let me take the next act.json here. It's
a little bit different. I have made
change here. Um, first of all, I can
also use the variables in here and they
will be replaced with the one from the
uh props file. You normally you would
get an error here because dollar sign
parenthesis version is not a valid
version but in this case it's a
placeholder and the value comes from the
props file. It also allows me to do
override because in this case you can
see the base URLs these are coming from
a props file. I have copied them in
here, but I have actually made a change
here which is specific for the B project
because I want a different help URL. I'm
still utilizing the base URL from the
props file, but I have made a small
change. So, I can customize this
specific project. I can also just choose
to leave other properties in, but this
is an efficient way to use the same
settings across. And for the last
project here,
I've already stripped away all the
properties. So let me go back into the
props file here and say actually I have
already made the revision change here. I
just haven't built. As you can see here,
we have fabricam a version 1.0000
in all projects. In this case, I have
made a change here to the vision
revision one. And if I go into this one
and do a build and see I actually get
the project build with a new version
because I got a one here and it picks it
up from the props file and uses that
during build. What we have done as well
is that we have also added support for
this in ALC. I mean it wouldn't it
wouldn't make sense if the props file
were only respected by Visual Studio
Code. is also respected by ALC. Use the
same mechanism to find the props file
and use that. So let me set the revision
to two here. This is setting an
environment variable in PowerShell. And
if I then use this PowerShell command
simply just getting all the directories
with only one letter and for each of
those I compile the projects.
So I can do that running the compiler
and you can see it runs
and now you can see over here I got the
version 0.2
there
and here. So the change
is happening to all my projects. I have
centralized centralized that in the
props file. This is a way more efficient
way of doing this in large repos with
many projects.
So to summarize what we have done here,
the file is found by name which means
that directory.app.prop.props.json
is the name of the file we're looking
for. The way it works is that from a
project we go upwards towards the root
and for the first file we found with a
directory.app app.props.json
name would take that one and uses that.
And as you just saw, this works for both
the Visual Studio. If you open a project
where you have removed the um some of
the props are using uh placeholders, it
will pick up the values from the props
file and it will work.
And also this is done at load time. So
when you start up Visual Studio Code, it
loads the props file, which also means
that if you make changes to the prop
file, add a new property, it will not be
picked up unless you reload.
If you build, it will work, but while
doing edit, it will not be picked up.
And properties are expanded during
package creation, which means that in
the generated packages, there are no
difference. They are the same no matter
whether the values comes from that.json
JSON file or they are picked up from the
props file. No different. And last,
there's a list of properties which we
currently support. We may add more in
the future. We'll probably do that. Um,
but this is what is supported right now.
I don't know if you noticed that before
when I built the uh all the projects I
used a slightly different command
and it solves a problem. This is which
is where's my ALC.ex XA.
I'm from the team that actually puts
LC.XA
on disk for you in the V6 and I always
have a hard time remembering where
exactly it is. So we have made a new way
of getting to our command line tools and
we decided to piggyback on a feature
called net tools which is the net
installation that provides you the
ability to download
tools packages which is essentially a
Nougat package with a special format
and the way you install um those tools
or command line tools is simply by the
net tool install and then this long name
and depending on whether you want the
Windows version, the Linux version or
the Mac OS version you can add that
Linux or osx
then you would do d- interactive
d-global and for now you need the
pre-release we plan to release it so you
will get a released version today it's
pre-release
and it's installed with an alias an al
alias which is an alias to the al tool
that we ship together with all the
command line tools the caveat with the
net tools packages is that you can only
add one alias. So we have decided that
the AL alias points to the AL tool and
then we will add all our tool chain into
the AL tool. So what you can do is you
can do AL help you can do a AL compile
to invoke the ALC and just put the rest
of the command line arguments there. Let
me show you how that works.
This is the PowerShell prompt I show you
before. And now let me just type. As you
noticed up here, actually I used the al
compile. If I just run al here, I get a
list of the supported commands for the
AL command here.
And let me try to use
the get application manifest.
Just created one called version two.
And if you look inside the manifest
here, you can actually see I got all the
values expanded. I got the URL base URL
fabricam. I got the revision point 2.
Everything is expanded. And this is what
we send to the server when you deploy an
application. So there's nothing magic
going on at the server. Everything is
done while you compile. And before I
actually mentioned that this is
crossplatform. You can also install this
for Linux. This happens to be running in
Windows Subsystem for Linux. And I have
already installed the Linux tool version
of this.
And here it tells me you can invoke the
tool using the command al. I think we
will lowerase that one before we ship it
in release because it's annoying to
uppercase it. And I can also here do a
get the same options and using
bash I can also compile all my packages
here. I have the same setup here with
three projects. So this would allow you
to more efficiently download the AL
command line tools in a pipeline. This
is the whole purpose of this. This is
what I have to show you today. I hope
you'll get inspired and go and update
your pipelines and make them more
efficient. We of course plan to uptake
this also in algo for GitHub. So if you
are using that already, you will get get
this functionality
soon or in the future at least.
That's all. Thank you for watching.